Guide to the Montrose Jonas Moses Papers, 1789-1960 RL.00917
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Montrose Jonas Moses papers
1789-1960
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Moses, Montrose Jonas, 1878-1934
RL.00917
25 Linear Feet
Drama critic, journalist, and author of works on American and European drama and on children's literature. Correspondence, research notes, literary drafts, scrapbooks, playbills, and photos, relating to Moses' career. Includes correspondence and research notes relating to Margaret Anglin, Sir James Matthew Barrie, Phillip Barry, Ethel Barrymore, Sarah Bernhardt, Billie Burke, Heinrich Conrad, Owen Davis, John Drinkwater, Edwin Forrest, James A. Herne, Henrik Ibsen, Sir Rabindranath Tagore, and other playwrights and actors prominent in the 19th and early 20th centuries; Moses' work as a reader for Thomas Y. Crowell Company and for Little, Brown and Company; and to the Ballet Russe, little theaters, entertaining troops at U. S. Army camps during World War I, Authors Club of New York, City College of New York, and Drama League of America. Correspondents include Winthrop Ames, Margaret Anglin, David Belasco, Henry Adams Bellows, May Friend Bennet, William Frederick Bigelow, Abbie Faarwell Brown, Richard Eugene Burton, Royal Jenkins Davis, William Crowell Edgar, John Erskine, William Clyde Fitch, Daniel Frohman, Hanniabal Hamlin Garland, Norman Bell Geddes, Harley Granville Granville-Barker, Hilary Abner Herbert, Hamilton Holt, Roland Holt, Henry Arthur Jones, Charles Rann Kennedy and his wife, Edith Wynne Matthison, Percy Mackaye, James Brander Matthews, Langdon Elwyn Mitchell, Arthur Huntington Nason, Eugene Gladstone O'Neill, Charles Fulton Cursler, William Lyon Phelps, Elmer Rice, Charles William Taussig, Augustus Thomas, Carl Van Doren, Eugene Walter, Kate Douglas (Smith) Wiggin, Percival Wilde, and Starke Young.
22,488 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Montrose Jonas Moses Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1972.
Biographical Note
Drama critic, journalist, and author of works on American and European drama and on children's literature.
Collection Overview
Collection contains papers of Montrose Jonas Moses (1878-1933), drama critic, journalist, and author of works on American and European drama and on children's literature, principally relating to his career. Correspondence pertains to his work as a reader for Thomas Y. Crowell Company and for Little, Brown and Company; his activities as liason between Little, Brown and Company and several authors under contract to prepare works for publication; his participation in the affairs of the Authors Club of New York and the Drama League of America, both at the national and local levels; and his own literary projects. Beginning in 1915, there are carbon copies of outgoing correspondence.
Notebooks, clippings, research notes, drafts, some correspondence, and other papers relate to Margaret Anglin, Sir James Matthew Barrie, Phillip Barry, Ethel Barrymore, Sarah Bernhardt, Billie Burke, Heinrich Conreid, Owen Davis, John Drinkwater, Edwin Forrest, James A. Herne, Henrik Ibsen, Sir Rabindranath Tagore, and other playwrights and actors prominent in the 19th and early 20th centuries; American and British drama; children's literature; baseball; the entertainment of troops at U.S. Army camps during World War I; the costs of medical care; and the development of regional or "little" theaters.
Scrapbooks contain the majority of his articles clipped from the journals and newspapers in which they appeared. Other papers include lectures and speeches; copies of works by other writers; financial papers consisting chiefly of royalty statements from publishers recording the sales of Moses's books; transcripts of Moses's weekly radio programs broadcast from 1930 to 1934 on the National Broadcasting Company network and on a local New York station; photographs of prominent actors and authors and of scenes from various plays; pictures of camp life in the U.S. Army during World War I; theater programs; scrapbooks of clippings from playbills of the last quarter of the 19th century; scrapbook with clippings concerning Sarah Bernhardt; scrapbook of items relating to Thomas Jonathan Jackson, compiled by Jackson's wife; and Moses's copy of The Tales of Mother Goose (Boston: 1903) with marginalia and annotations written by Moses.
Correspondents include Winthrop Ames, Margaret Anglin, David Belasco, Henry Adams Bellows, May Friend Bennett, William Frederick Bigelow, Abbie Farwell Brown, Richard Eugene Burton, Royal Jenkins Davis, William Crowell Edgar, John Erskine, William Clyde Fitch, Daniel Frohman, Hamlin Garland, Norman Bel Geddes, Harley Granville Granville-Barker, Hilary Abner Herbert, Hamilton Holt, Roland Holt, Henry Arthur Jones, Charles Rann Kennedy, Frederick Koch, Percy MacKaye, James Brander Matthews, Edith Wynne Matthison, Langdon Elwyn Mitchell, Arthur Huntington Nason, Eugene Gladstone O'Neill, Charles Fulton Oursler, William Lyon Phelps, Elmer Rice, Charles William Taussig, Augustus Thomas, Carl Van Doren, Eugene Walter, Kate Douglas (Smith) Wiggin, Percival Wilde, and Stark Young.
Drama -- History and criticism; Litterateurs; New York (N.Y.) -- Intellectual life; English literature -- History and criticism; Journalists -- New York (State) -- New York; Moses, Montrose Jonas, 1878-1934; Moses, Montrose Jonas, 1878-1934
- Correspondence Series, 1890-1960 and undated, 28 boxes
  - Correspondence, 1890 - 1911 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1912 - 1913 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1914 - 1915 May (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1915 June - 1916 Jan. (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1916 Feb. - Aug. 16 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1916 Aug. 17 - 1917 March 12 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1917 March 13 - Sept. 19 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1917 Sept. 20 - 1918 Feb. (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1918 March - Dec. (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1919 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1920-1921 March (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1921 Apr. - 1922 June (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, 1922 July - 1923 April (Box 13)
  - Correspondence, 1923 May - 1924 April (Box 14)
  - Correspondence, 1924 May - 1925 Feb. (Box 15)
  - Correspondence, 1925 March - Sept 14 (Box 16)
  - Correspondence, 1925 Sept 15 - 1926 Feb. (Box 17)
  - Correspondence, 1926 March - Sept. 17 (Box 18)
  - Correspondence, 1926 Sept. 18 - 1927 Aug. (Box 19)
  - Correspondence, 1927 Sept. - 1928 Oct. (Box 20)
  - Correspondence, 1928 Nov. - 1929 July (Box 21)
  - Correspondence, 1929 Aug. - 1930 Aug. (Box 22)
  - Correspondence, 1930 Sept. - 1931 April (Box 23)
  - Correspondence, 1931 May - Dec. (Box 24)
  - Correspondence, 1932 Jan.- May (Box 25)
  - Correspondence, 1932 June - 1933 Feb. (Box 26)
  - Correspondence, 1933 March - Dec. (Box 27)
  - Correspondence, 1934-1960, undated. (Box 28)
- Writings and Notes Series, 64 boxes
  - American Drama (Box 28)
  - American Drama from 1860-1918 (Box 28)
  - The American Dramatist (Box 28)
  - American Drama - Pictorial History (Chapts 1-13) (Box 29)
  - American Drama - Pictorial History (Chapts 14-17 and Typed Copy) (Box 30)
  - American Drama - Pictorial History (Carbon Copy) (Box 31)
  - American Drama - Pictorial History (Miscellaneous Drafts and Notes) (Box 32)
  - American Drama - Pictorial History (Miscellaneous Notes) (Box 33)
  - American Drama - Representative Plays (Drafts) (Box 34)
  - American Drama - Representative Plays (Notes) (Box 35)
  - American Drama - Representative Plays (Notes) (Box 36)
  - American Drama - Miscellany, 1901-1915 (Box 37)
  - American Drama - Miscellany, 1916-1928 (Box 38)
  - American Drama - Miscellany, 1929-1934 and undated. (Box 39)
  - American Drama - Miscellany, undated and miscellaneous notes (Box 40)
  - American Drama - Notebooks 1-5 (Box 41)
  - American Drama - Notebooks 6-9 (Box 42)
  - American Drama - Notebooks 10-14 (Box 43)
  - American Drama - Notebooks 15-20 (Box 44)
  - American Drama - Notebooks 21-23 (Box 45)
  - American Drama - Notebooks 24-37 (Box 46)
  - Anglin (Box 47)
  - Barrie (Box 47)
  - Barrymore (Box 47)
  - Belasco (Box 48)
  - Bernhardt (Box 49)
  - "Blue Monday" (Box 49)
  - "Books for the Guest Room." (Box 50)
  - British Drama- Miscellany, 1904-1933 and undated. (Box 50)
  - British Drama - Miscellaneous Notes (Box 51)
  - British Drama - Notebooks 1-31 (Box 51)
  - British Drama - Notebooks 32-39 (Box 52)
  - Burke (Box 53)
  - Children's Literature (Box 53)
  - Children's Literature: Ring Up the Curtain (Box 54)
  - Children's Literature: Random Essays (Box 54)
  - Children's Literature: Miscellany, 1899-1908 (Box 54)
  - Children's Literature: Miscellany, 1903-1926 (Box 55)
  - Children's Literature: Miscellaneous Notes (Box 55)
  - Children's Literature: Notebook 1 (Box 55)
  - Children's Literature: Notebooks 2-40 (Box 56)
  - Children's Literature: Notebooks 41-68 (Box 57)
  - Children's Literature: Notebooks 69-81 (Box 58)
  - Children's Literature: Notebooks 82-95 (Box 59)
  - Children's Literature: Notebooks 96-97 (Box 60)
  - Children's Literature: Notebooks 98-100 (Box 61)
  - Collier's Encyclopedia (Box 62)
  - Conried (Box 62)
  - Continental Drama (Box 62)
  - Continental Drama (Box 63)
  - Cooper-Misc Notes; Notebooks 1-17 (Box 63)
  - Cooper, Notebooks 18-21 (Box 64)
  - Cowl (Box 65)
  - Dictionary of American Biography (Box 65)
  - Doctor, How Much? (Box 66)
  - Dramas of Modernism (Box 67)
  - Drinkwater (Box 67)
  - Education (Box 67)
  - Fitch - Correspondence: Copies of letters for Clyde Fitch and his Letters (Box 68)
  - Fitch - Clyde Fitch and his Letters (Typed Draft, Notes) (Box 69)
  - Fitch - Clyde Fitch and his Letters (Notes, Proofs) (Box 70)
  - Fitch - Miscellany (Box 71)
  - Forrest (Box 72)
  - Forrest (Box 73)
  - Francesca da Rimini (Box 73)
  - "Frontiers of American Drama" (Box 74)
  - Granville-Barker (Box 74)
  - "History as Told in Pictures" (Box 74)
  - "History as Told in Pictures" (Box 75)
  - Holt (Box 76)
  - Ibsen (Box 76)
  - Interviews (Box 76)
  - Kennedy (Box 76)
  - Little Theaters (Box 77)
  - Little Theaters (Box 78)
  - Lodge (Box 78)
  - Marlowe (Box 78)
  - Masefield (Box 78)
  - Maeterlinck (Box 79)
  - The Mishap of an Automobilist (Box 79)
  - "New Timber" (Box 79)
  - Obergammerau (Box 79)
  - O'Neill (Box 80)
  - "Panorama of Baseball" (Box 80)
  - "Panorama of Baseball" (Box 81)
  - Religious Drama (Box 81)
  - Plunkett (Box 81)
  - Reports (Box 81)
  - Rothafel (Box 81)
  - Shaw (Box 81)
  - Stage History (Box 82)
  - Stage Scenery (Box 82)
  - Stoddard (Box 82)
  - Tagore (Box 82)
  - Washington (Box 83)
  - World War I, 1915-1919 (Box 83)
  - World War I, undated. (Box 84)
  - Yancey (Box 84)
  - Miscellany, 1892-1911 (Box 84)
  - Miscellany, 1912 - 1920 Nov. (Box 85)
  - Miscellany, 1920 Dec. - 1933 (Box 86)
  - Miscellany, undated. (Box 87)
  - Miscellany, undated. (Box 88)
  - Miscellaneous Notes (Box 88)
  - Volumes 1-3 (Box 88)
  - Volumes 4-24 (Box 89)
  - Volumes 25-31 (Box 90)
  - Volumes 32-33 (Box 91)
  - Writings by Others: A-L (Box 92)
  - Writings by Others: M-Z (Box 93)
- Speeches and Lectures Series 1914-1933 and undated, 3 boxes
  - Speeches and Lectures, 1914-1933 (Box 94)
  - Speeches and Lectures, undated. (Box 95)
  - Speeches and Lectures, undated. (Box 96)
- Radio Broadcasts Series, 1930-1934 and undated, 5 boxes
  - Radio Broadcasts: 1930 (Box 96)
  - Radio Broadcasts: 1931 Jan.-July (Box 97)
  - Radio Broadcasts: 1931 Aug.-1932 Jan. (Box 98)
  - Radio Broadcasts: 1932 Feb.-March (Box 99)
  - Radio Broadcasts: 1932 April-1934 and undated. (Box 100)
- Financial Papers Series, 1903-1934 and undated, 2 boxes
  - Financial Papers: 1903-1927 (Box 101)
  - Financial Papers: 1928-1934 and undated. (Box 102)
- Miscellany Series, 1923-1934 and undated, 2 boxes
  - Drama League (Box 103)
  - Author's Club, 1923-1931 (Box 103)
  - Author's Club, 1932-1934 and undated. (Box 104)
- Clippings Series, 1863-1934 and undated, 4 boxes
  - Clippings, 1863-1921 (Box 104)
  - Clippings, 1920-1931 (Box 105)
  - Clippings, 1932-1934 and undated. (Box 106)
  - Clippings, undated. (Box 107)
  - Book Review (Box 107)
- Printed Materials Series, 1837-1934 and undated, 11 boxes
  - Printed Material, 1914-1932 (Box 108)
  - Printed Material, 1933-1944 (Box 109)
  - Printed Material: Theater Programs, 1837-1905 (Box 110)
  - Printed Material: Theater Programs, 1905-1909 (Box 111)
  - Printed Material: Theater Programs, 1909, Nov.- 1910, Oct. (Box 112)
  - Printed Material: Theater Programs, 1910, Nov.- 1911 (Box 113)
  - Printed Material: Theater Programs, 1911-1914 (Box 114)
  - Printed Material: Theater Programs,1914-1916 (Box 115)
  - Printed Material: Theater Programs, 1916-1918 (Box 116)
  - Printed Material: Theater Programs, 1919-1944 (Box 117)
  - Printed Material: Theater Programs, undated. (Box 118)
- Volumes Series, 5 boxes, 4 bound volumes
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes scrapbooks, diaries, and other volumes.
  - Volumes: Desk Diary (Box 118)
  - Volumes: Scrapbooks 1-4 (Box 119)
  - Volumes: Scrapbooks 5-8 (Box 120)
  - Volumes: Scrapbooks 9-10 (Box 121)
  - Volumes: Scrapbook, 1916-1919 (Box 147)
  - Volumes: Diary (Box 147)
  - Volume: Obergammerau and its Passion Play (Box 127)
  - Volumes: (Annotated and interleaved with notes by Moses) (Box 130)
    Includes George H. Nettleton, English Drama of the Restoration and Eighteenth Century; Percival Wilde, The Craftsmanship of the One Act Play; and Charles Lamb's Essays.
  - Volume (Volume L:788)
  - Volume (Volume L:795)
  - Volume (Volume L:796)
  - Volume (Volume L:797)
- Photographs Series, 6 boxes
  - Photographs: A-D (Box 122)
  - Photographs: E-G (Box 123)
  - Photographs: H-M (Box 124)
  - Photographs: N-V; World War I (Box 125)
  - Photographs: W-Z; Miscellaneous (Box 126)
  - Glass plate negatives (Box 130)
  - Pictures: A-F (Box 144)
  - Pictures: G-Z (Box 145)
  - Pictures: Miscellaneous, Scrapbook re Jackson (Box 146)
- Diaries Series, 1 box
  - Diaries - Photocopies (Box 128)
- Notecards Series, 13 boxes
  - Notecards: Miscellaneous Bibliography, A-E (Box 131)
  - Notecards: Miscellaneous Bibliography: F-Mat (Box 132)
  - Notecards: Miscellaneous Bibliography: Mau-Shad (Box 133)
  - Notecards: Miscellaneous Bibliography: Shak-Z (Box 134)
  - Notecards: No 2 American Dream (Box 135)
  - Notecards: No 2 American Dream, cont. (Box 136)
  - Unlabeled (Box 136)
  - Notecards: Notes and Bibliography (Box 137)
  - Unlabeled (Box 137)
  - Notecards: Miscellaneous Bibliography (Box 138)
  - Miscellaneous Lectures (Box 138)
  - Unlabeled (Box 138)
  - Notecards: Literature of the South (Box 139)
  - Notecards: Literature of the South, cont. (Box 140)
  - Notecards: Literature of the South, cont. (Box 141)
  - Notecards: Maeterlinck (Box 142)
  - Notecards: Unlabeled (Box 142)
  - Notecards: Unlabeled (Box 143)